{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One side at this battle failed to penetrate earthworks along the Rodriguez Canal, suffering over two thousand casualties to the Americans’ seventy-one. British general Edward Pakenham was killed while Jean Lafitte assisted the victors in this battle, fought two weeks after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent that ended the War of 1812. For ten points, name this military victory for Andrew Jackson, which took place outside a large city in Louisiana.",
      "answer": "Battle of New Orleans A"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this country’s colonies, named Port Royal, was captured by the British in 1710, leading to the Great Expulsion of people from this country to regions farther south. This country chose to keep its sugar-producing colonies of Guadeloupe and Martinique instead of much of their territory in continental North America that included Upper Canada. For ten points, name this country that, after fighting Great Britain in the Seven Years War, ceded its colony of Quebec.",
      "answer": "France or French Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this body was conceived by 11-year old Venetia Burney and announced in 1930. ThRough Percival Lowell initially predicted this body’s existence, Clyde Tombaugh discovered it using an astrograph. Photographs of this body from 12,500 kilometers were taken by the New Horizons space probe in July 2015. For ten points, name this body that was the smallest planet in our solar system prior to its controversial reclassification as a dwarf planet in 2006.",
      "answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to duel Humphrey Marshall after proposing a law that banned British cloth in favor of homespun cloth. This man argued with Andrew Jackson over the funding of the Maysville Road as Dpart of the American System. They feuded again when this Speaker of the House awarded the Election of 1824 to John Quincy Adams as part of a “corrupt bargain.” For ten points, name this Kentucky senator, known as the “Great Compromiser.”",
      "answer": "Henry Clay"
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty was founded by an emperor who established a secret police force known as the Embroidered Uniform Guard. That emperor’s grandson died at the hands of his uncle, Zhu Di, who became the Yongle [yong-luh] Emperor. The Yongle Emperor employed the eunuch Zheng He [zhung-huh] to command his treasure fleet and successfully spread Chinese influence as far as the Persian Gulf. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that ruled from 1368 to 1644, perhaps best known today for its fine ceramics.",
      "answer": "Ming Dynasty T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This Englishman’s belief that government must maintain “life, liberty, and estate” was echoed by Thomas Jefferson. He believed that the mind was born without any pre-established ideas, his “tabula rasa.” That concept was discussed in An Essay Concerning Human Understanding. He’s not Rousseau, but this philosopher argued for a social contract in another of his most famous works. For ten points, F name this philosopher and author of Two Treatises of Government.",
      "answer": "John Locke"
    },
    {
      "question": "Arrivals at this place were asked a series of questions, controversially including the amount of money they carried, and the National Origins Act of 1924 imposed race-based quotas on the operations of this place. By the time this place closed in 1954, over 12 million people had passed through it. For ten points, identify this New York island which during the first half of the 20th century was the U.S.’s busiest A immigrant inspection port.",
      "answer": "Ellis Island"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Velazquez painting of this figure was attacked by suffragette Mary Richardson. A faceless depiction of this figure was discovered in 1908 by Joseph Szombathy in the village of Willendorf. In another painting, this figure is blown to shore by Zephyrus and stands on a giant shell. An armless statue discovered on the island of Milos depicts, for ten points, what goddess whose birth is depicted in a painting by Sandro Botticelli? R",
      "answer": [
        "Venus",
        "Aphrodite",
        "Venus of Willendorf, Rokeby Venus, Venus de Milo,",
        "Birth of Venus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s navy fought off one attack by using fireships to thwart enemies at the battle of Gravelines [grav-LEEN]. One of this ruler’s admirals launched a daring raid on Cadiz, boasting he had “singed the beard” of a rival king. This patron of Francis Drake gave the Tilbury speech, where this ruler declared she had the “heart and stomach of a king” in the face of invasion from the Spanish Armada. For ten points, name this daughter of Henry VIII, the “virgin queen” of England. D",
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Girolamo Frescobaldi and Jean Lully Batiste were composers from the early part of this period. This period of music was significant for ushering in the transition from modal to tonal styles, and music from this period tended to be dense and complex, forming a polyphony of voices through arrangements such as the fugue. For ten points, identify this period of music named after the Portuguese word for “misshapen pearl,” lasting from roughly 1600-1750 and including notable composers such as Bach and Handel.",
      "answer": "Baroque T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man unsuccessfully conspired to get Thomas Pinckney elected president in 1796. This man was married to Eliza Schuyler [SKY-lur], but had an affaFir with Maria Reynolds. This man who established the U.S. Mint, and was also the primary author of the Federalist Papers, suggested a controversial tax on a particular alcoholic beverage while a member of George Washington’s cabinet. For ten points, name this first Secretary of the Treasury, depicted on the U.S. $10 bill.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Washington, D.C. building, currently housing the office of Steve Mnuchin, is featured on the back of the U.S. Ten dollar bill? A",
        "answer": "Treasury Building"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The world’s tallest statue of a woman commemorates this battle and is known as “The Motherland Calls.” Soldiers stationed at Kalach-on-the-Don were encircled as part of this battle’s Operation Uranus. A speech by Adolf Hitler named after this battle ends with him exclaiming “I do not want a second Verdun there!” An attempt to provide supplies to one side during Operation Winter Storm was thwarted by terrible weather at this 1942-43 battle. Over 1.7 million casualties occurred at, for ten points, what massive World War Two battle, where Germany surrendered to the Soviet Union? R",
        "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The initial German goal at the Battle of Stalingrad was to block this river on which Stalingrad lay, the longest river in Europe.",
        "answer": "Volga"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The original land that made up this city during colonial times was bought by Jacob Van Curler and was used to establish Fort Hoop. This city derived its name from the English home town of Samuel Stone D who brought settlers to this location from what is now Cambridge, Massachusetts. A treaty between New Netherland and the residents of this city in New England established a boundary along its colony’s namesake river. A state quarter depicts a tree in this city where residents secretly hid a colonial charter. Located near New Haven, for ten points, name this capital of Connecticut.",
        "answer": "Hartford, Connecticut"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1944, one of the worst fire disasters in U.S. history occurred in Hartford where 167 people were killed at a performance given by Ringling Brothers and Barnum and Bailey. What kind of performance was this?",
        "answer": "Circus T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This vessel’s remains are located at the Newport News Mariners Museum. The namesake of a type of warship with revolving gun turrets, this vessel was designed by John Ericcson, built in Brooklyn, and mocked as a “cheesebox on a raft.” This warship’s arrival saved the USS Minnesota, and Lt. John Worden commanded it during its best known action at Hampton Roads, in which it faced a converted wooden F craft formerly known as the Merrimack. For ten points, name this Civil War ironclad warship that fought for the Union against the CSS Virginia.",
        "answer": "USS Monitor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Monitor sank near this cape off North Carolina, named for a Native American tribe on the island of Croatoan, called the “Graveyard of the Atlantic.”",
        "answer": "Cape Hatteras A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Carillon at this site was created by Coca-Cola for the 1964 World’s Fair. The largest bas-relief sculpture in the world can be found at this site. A 2013 bell-ringing was held here during the fiftieth anniversary of Martin Luther King’s “I Have a Dream Speech” in which King said “Let Freedom Ring from [this site] of Georgia.” After the release of Birth of a Nation, this monument became the site of the founding of the second Ku Klux Klan. Made of quartz monzonite, this monument contains depictions of Jefferson Davis and Robert E. Lee. For ten points, name this Confederate equivalent of Mount Rushmore.",
        "answer": "Stone Mountain Park R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stone Mountain Park opened on April 14 of this year, 100 years to the day after the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.",
        "answer": "1965"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first person to hold this position once vomited on stage during an election debate. John MacDonald was the second-longest holder of this position, after only William Lyon Mackenzie King. Another holder of this position enforced the only peacetime usage of the War Measures Act in response D to the October Crisis and was the father of the current holder of this position, who succeeded Stephen Harper. For ten points, name this position currently held by Justin Trudeau.",
        "answer": "Prime Minister of Canada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Canadian Prime Minister Lester B. Pearson won the 1957 Nobel Peace Prize for his role in resolving the conflict over what strategic waterway?",
        "answer": "Suez Canal T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Boer War, this man served as a journalist and escaped from prison after being captured by Boer troops. In one speech, this man urged his countrymen to fight on the beaches and landing areas and never give up. This man claimed that he had nothing to offer but “blood, toil, sweat, and tears.” After the resignation of Neville Chamberlain, this man rose to his highest position of Prime Minister and F led the U.K.’s staunch resistance to Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this influential British leader.",
        "answer": "Winston Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill’s resolve remained unshaken despite facing this Nazi bombing campaign from September 1940 to May 1941. Its name is taken from the German word for “Lightning.”",
        "answer": "The Blitz A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of San Juan Hill",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which the battle took place F",
          "answer": "Spanish-American War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future U.S. president who led a volunteer unit",
          "answer": [
            "Theodore Roosevelt",
            "Teddy Rooosevelt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliterative nickname of the the U.S. volunteer cavalry unit led by that future president",
          "answer": "Rough Riders A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country in which the battle took place",
          "answer": "Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of the African-American regular cavalry unit that was first to the top of Kettle Hill",
          "answer": "Buffalo Soldiers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future commander of the American Expeditionary Forces in World War One who fought on Kettle Hill R",
          "answer": "John J. Pershing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapon credited with breaking the will of the Spanish, an early type of machine gun",
          "answer": "Gatling gun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Confederate general who commanded the U.S. cavalry after leaving his sickbed, nicknamed “Fighting Joe”",
          "answer": "Joseph Wheeler D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutions of 1848",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent where the majority of the noted revolutions took place F",
          "answer": "Europe"
        },
        {
          "question": "System that tied peasants to land, abolished in Austria",
          "answer": "Serfdom"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was the site of the June Days, leading to the establishment of the Second Republic",
          "answer": "Paris A"
        },
        {
          "question": "French king from the House of Orleans forced to abdicate by the revolution",
          "answer": "Louis Philippe I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian chancellor who resigned due to the revolution",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose revolution was led by Lajos [LAH-johsh] Kossuth",
          "answer": "Hungary R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian field marshal who crushed the revolution in Vienna",
          "answer": "Joseph Radetzky"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope whose opposition to the unification of Italy led to revolution",
          "answer": "Pius IX D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Southeast Asian Countries",
      "prompt": "Name the modern Southeast Asian country...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "That declared independence from Spain in 1898 and gained it from the US in 1946 F",
          "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the Battle of Dien Bien Phu was fought, once divided into North and South",
          "answer": "Socialist Republic of Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the Khmer Rouge led by Pol Pot carried out genocide resulting in the infamous “killing fields”",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Cambodia",
            "Kampuchea A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Once led by Lee Kuan Yew and founded as a colony by Stamford Raffles",
          "answer": "Republic of Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Whose president Suharto led from its capital Jakarta",
          "answer": "Republic of Indonesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to 1990 Nobel Peach Prize winner Aung San Suu Kyi [CHEE], its first State Counsellor",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of the Union of Myanmar",
            "Burma R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of military coups against Thaksin Shinawatra and his sister Yingluck",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Once led by Mahathir Mohamad and embroiled in the 1MDB political scandal.",
          "answer": "Malaysia D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Perhaps the first person to serve in this role in the U.S. was former journalist Judson Welliver during the administrations of HardinFg and Coolidge. Much of Profiles in Courage was co-written by another person with this role named Ted Sorenson. While holding this role during Nixon’s administration, (20 pts)",
        "William Safire created the term “nattering nabobs of negativism.” Another person in this role, Peggy Noonan, coined the phrases “a kinder, gentler nation” and “Read my (10 pts)",
        "lips: no new taxes.” For ten points, name this profession of those who write inaugural comments and presidential State of the Union comments."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Presidential Speechwriters",
        "equivalents A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these two countries refused to use force to put down the revolt of Colonel Ahmed Urabi, prompting the other to intervene militarily. Another incident between these two countries featured a territorial dispute in Sudan and ended with a troop standoff in (20 pts)",
        "Fashoda. These two countries later worked with David Ben-Gurion in Operation Musketeer, deploying paratroopers to thwart Gamel Abdel Nasser’s (10 pts)",
        "nationalization of a waterway. For ten points, name these two European powers that joined forces in the Suez Crisis."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom",
        "UK, Britain,",
        "England and France 3RNicolay de Caveri created one of these items based on another that a fellow countryman smuggled out of Portugal. Fifty-three of these were collected by Abraham Ortelius to create the Theatrum Orbis Terrarum. The preservation of + angles in a 1569 object of this type resulted in several key distortions. Martin Waldeseemuller’s Universalis Cosmographia was an object of this type in which the name * Amerigo Vespucci was used to identify certain new landmasses. The Mercator Projection is an example of, for ten points, what cartographic objects? ANSWER: Maps D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this decade, the Advanced Producers’ Co-operatives were first established. In this decade, during the Lushan [loo-SHAN] Conference, General Peng Dehuai [pun duh-HWHY] was purged as part of the (20 pts)",
        "Anti-Rightist Movement. A program named after a poem about the Warring States period began in this decade. Backyard steel production was part of a campaign launched in this decade that led to a (10 pts)",
        "famine that killed millions. For ten points, name this decade that included China’s Hundred Flowers Campaign and the Great Leap Forward."
      ],
      "answer": "1950s"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This program was named by Abe Silverstein and was defended in a speech that stated things like it are done “not because they are easy, but because they are hard.” This program received a major setback in 1967 after (20 pts)",
        "Ed White, Roger Chaffee, and Gus Grissom were killed in an accident during a test. After the eleventh mission of this program landed in the Sea of (10 pts)",
        "Tranquility, Neil Armstrong described his first step on the moon as “one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.” For ten points, name this NASA manned space program that took men to the moon."
      ],
      "answer": "Apollo program"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Max Eastman translated a three-volume history written by this man as well as a work in which this man claims that one leader is engaging in ineffective “zigzags” in economic policy. That work by this man accuses a rival of engaging in “Bonapartism” and is titled (20 pts)",
        "The Revolution Betrayed. In one essay, this man claims that “the task of arming the F revolution falls with all its weight upon the proletariat,” which is in reference to his desire to maintain the (10 pts)",
        "Red Army that he created. For ten points, name this Leftist Russian revolutionary whose assassination was ordered by Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": "Leon Trotsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The financial troubles behind the construction of this structure caused a scandal for a company created by Ferdinand de Lesseps and led to the Spooner Act. A namesake A “Zone” for this structure was formed in a treaty between John Hay and Philippe-Jean (20 pts)",
        "Bunau-Varilla. In a later treaty, Jimmy Carter agreed to give up control of this structure to a country led by Omar Torrijos. Many of those who built this structure suffered (10 pts)",
        "Yellow Fever, but its construction allowed ships to bypass South America’s Cape Horn. For ten points, name this structure that connects the Caribbean Sea and the Pacific through a Central American country."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a famous confrontation with Valerian Zorin, this man said, “I do not have your talent forRobfuscation” and that this man would potentially wait for a “yes or no” answer “until (20 pts)",
        "hell freezes over.” This man was a member of a noted family including his father, the U.S. Vice President under Grover Cleveland. In 1949, this man succeeded Dwight Green as governor of Illinois before running in (10 pts)",
        "two presidential elections as the Democratic nominee, losing both times to a World War Two five-star general. For ten points, name this politician who lost those elections to Dwight Eisenhower."
      ],
      "answer": "Adlai Ewing Stevenson II D"
    }
  ]
}